Guide to the Paul Joseph Cohen Papers SC1264
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Paul Joseph Cohen papers
1981-2015
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Cohen, Paul J.
SC1264
4 Linear Feet 6 boxes
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Joseph Cohen won two of the most prestigious awards in mathematics—in completely different fields. He won the American Mathematical Society's Bôcher Prize in 1964 for analysis and the Fields Medal, considered the "Nobel Prize" of mathematics, in 1966 for logic.
"Paul Cohen was one of the most brilliant mathematicians of the 20th century," said Princeton Math Professor Peter Sarnak, who received his doctorate from Stanford in 1980 under Cohen's direction. "Like many great mathematicians, his mathematical interests and contributions were very broad, ranging from mathematical analysis and differential equations to mathematical logic and number theory. This breadth was highlighted in a conference held at Stanford last September celebrating Cohen's work and his 72nd birthday. The gathering consisted of leading experts in different fields who normally would not find themselves listening to the same set of lectures."
Stanford Mathematics Chair Yasha Eliashberg, the Herald L. and Caroline L. Ritch Professor in the School of Humanities and Sciences, was among many mathematicians who recalled Cohen's passion for tackling extremely difficult, longstanding mathematical problems—and solving them. "His solution of the Continuum Hypothesis will be remembered as one of the crown achievements of mathematics in the last 50 years, along with Andrew Wiles's proof of Fermat's Last Theorem and the recent proof of the Poincaré conjecture by Grigori Perelman," Eliashberg said.
"He is best known for his solution of the first of the 23 problems that the German mathematician David Hilbert posed in his very influential address to the International Mathematical Union in 1900," Sarnak said. "By the 1950s, after the work of Gödel, this problem, known as the 'Continuum Hypothesis,' had become the central one in the set theory."
In the late 1870s, German mathematician Georg Cantor put forth a hypothesis that said any infinite subset of the set of all real numbers can be put into one-to-one correspondence either with the set of integers or with the set of all real numbers. All attempts to prove or disprove this conjecture failed until 1938, when Kurt Gödel showed it was impossible to disprove the continuum hypothesis.
Despite having never worked in set theory, Cohen proved the extremely surprising result that both the Continuum Hypothesis and the Axiom of Choice—two of the most basic ideas in mathematics—were actually undecidable using the axioms of set theory. This result, which meant that conventional mathematics could neither prove nor disprove concrete and well known mathematical assertions, caused healthy turbulence among philosophers, logicians and mathematicians concerned with the concept of truth.
"Kurt Gödel, whose work in the 1930s on the consistency of the continuum hypothesis was completed by Cohen's proof of its independence from the usual axioms of set theory, lauded Cohen's work as 'no doubt...the greatest advance in the foundations of set theory since its axiomatization,'" wrote Solomon Feferman, an emeritus professor of mathematics and philosophy famed for work in logic, in an e-mail interview.
Alexander S. Kechris, a descriptive set theorist at Caltech, said Cohen invented and used in his independence proofs a fundamental mathematical technique called forcing. "It has since become a major tool in modern mathematical logic," Kechris said. Feferman, the Patrick Suppes Family Professor of Humanities and Sciences, Emeritus, explained that forcing is used to construct unusual models of the axioms of set theory, whereby statements are made true in stages and forced to remain so in all further stages.
Angus MacIntyre, a professor of applied logic at Queen Mary, University of London, said Cohen "had done work that should long outlast our times. For mathematical logic, and the broader culture that surrounds it, his name belongs with that of Gödel. Nothing more dramatic than their work has happened in the history of the subject."
Life path Cohen was born April 2, 1934, in Long Branch, N.J., to parents Abraham and Minnie, both Jewish immigrants from Poland. According to a 1968 article from the Trenton Evening Times, Cohen, the youngest of four children, was only nine years old when his sister Sylvia checked out a book about calculus from a New York library for him. Librarians were reluctant to let her have the book, much less for her younger brother, arguing that even some college professors didn't understand calculus.
Cohen grew up in Brooklyn and graduated from Stuyvesant High School in New York City in 1950. He attended Brooklyn College from 1950 to 1953 but left before receiving a bachelor's degree when he learned he could pursue graduate studies in Chicago with just two years of college under his belt. From the University of Chicago's Mathematics Department, he received a master's degree in 1954 and a doctorate in 1958. He wrote his thesis, "Topics in the Theory of Uniqueness of Trigonometric Series," under the supervision of Antoni Zygmund.
Before the award of his doctorate, Cohen taught math at the University of Rochester from 1957 to 1958. He also taught at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology during the 1958-59 academic year. From 1959 to 1961, he was a fellow at Princeton's Institute for Advanced Study.
Cohen joined Stanford's faculty in 1961 as an assistant professor of mathematics, becoming an associate professor in 1962, the year he received an Alfred P. Sloan research fellowship. In 1963, he won a Research Corp. Award for "his proof of the independence of the continuum hypothesis and of the axiom of choice, and initiating a whole series of advances in the field." He became a full professor in 1964.
"He inspired me when I was a young mathematician," said MacIntyre, a graduate student at Stanford from 1964 to 1967. "I never heard him lecture on set theory, but rather on algebraic geometry and p-adic fields. He had a very special style, full of enthusiasm and very 'hands on.' He used as little general theory as possible and always conveyed a sense that he got to the heart of things. His techniques, even in something as abstract as set theory, were very constructive. He was dauntingly clever, and one would have had to be naïve or exceptionally altruistic to put one's 'hardest problem' to the Paul I knew in the '60s."
Sarnak agreed: "Cohen was a dynamic and enthusiastic lecturer and teacher. He made mathematics look simple and unified. He was always eager to share his many ideas and insights in diverse fields. His passion for mathematics never waned."
At a White House ceremony on Feb. 13, 1968, President Johnson presented him with the 1967 National Medal of Science for "epoch-making results in mathematical logic which have enlivened and broadened investigations in the foundation of mathematics." Calling Cohen "one of the most brilliant of mathematical logicians," Johnson said: "His work has greatly influenced the foundation and development of mathematics."
In 1972, Cohen became the first holder of the Marjorie Mhoon Fair Professorship in Quantitative Science. Author of the book Set Theory and the Continuum Hypothesis, he was a member of the National Academy of Sciences, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Mathematical Society and the American Philosophical Society. He retired in 2004 but continued to teach until this quarter.
"In recent years, Cohen continued to work on notoriously difficult problems and in particular the Riemann Hypothesis, which is problem eight on Hilbert's list," Sarnak said. "As of today this problem remains unsolved."
Cohen played piano and violin and sang in a Stanford chorus and in a Swedish folk group, according to his son Charles. He spoke Swedish, French, Spanish, German and Yiddish and traveled widely, taking sabbaticals in England, Sweden, France and Hawaii. He met his wife, Christina, from the Swedish town of Malung, during a cruise from Stockholm to Leningrad in the summer of 1962. They married on Oct. 10, 1963.
Cohen is survived by wife Christina Cohen of Stanford; sister Tobel Cosiol of San Jose, Costa Rica; brother Ruby Cassel of Brooklyn, N.Y.; twin sons Eric and Steven Cohen of Los Angeles, Calif., and son Charles Cohen and his wife, Andreea, of Boston, Mass.
Source: http://news.stanford.edu/news/2007/april4/cohen-040407.html
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of Cohen's photographs, audiovisual materials, and computer files.
Mathematics.; Mathematics.; Mathematics -- Scientific applications.; Mathematics -- Scientific applications.; Mathematics -- Study and teaching (Higher).; Mathematics -- Study and teaching (Higher).; Mathematics -- History -- 20th century.; Mathematics -- History -- 20th century.; Cohen, Paul J.; Cohen, Paul J.; Cohen, Paul J.; Cohen, Paul J.; Cohen, Paul J.
- Photographs
  - Travel, Family, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Travel (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - unlabeled (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Audiovisual material
  - There Once Was A Town, 2000; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Kreisel Vienna, 2006 May 1; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Paul's TV, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Taft house and Vista House, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Burbank Houses Los Feliz Wiletta, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Alcyona House, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mikado, 1987; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Japanese TV, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Mom's tape Maltese Falcon, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mom's Tape West Side Story, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Paul's Tape Mrs. Chase at R. R. Stats Japanese TV, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Japanese TV, Japanese News, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bertil, Ewa etc. Warriors Japanese TV, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Paul's tape, House Inventory Japanese TV, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Kreisel interview Vienna, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Book tape I important, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Marten Davis some Paul, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - unlabeled, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - unlabeled, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Yansan To = Japanese video, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Posmer's, Charles playing Tennis with Paul, Stein, P.A. Train Dept., Stein Parlon Campus, 1982; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Paul's tape, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Paul's tape Family Friends, 1987 May 28; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Paul's tape, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Eric Mad About You, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Japanese …, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Japanese Lessons, 2015; 6_02; audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
  - Side A Music Japanese, 2015; 6_03; audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
  - Lesson 30, Songs, 6_04; audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
  - Untitled, 6_05; audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
  - Untitled, 6_06; audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
  - Lessons 15 16 17; Roger Reynolds, 6_07; audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
  - Untitled, 6_08; audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
  - Sweden, 2002 Summer; 6_09; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - New Booth, 6_10; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - LA Hours, 6_11; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Costa Rica, 2001 jul; 6_12; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Important, 6_13; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - PJ Cohen 2, 2001 Nov 07; 6_14; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Cohen Talk At Vienna; Godel Conference, 2006; 6_15; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen House, 6_16; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen (Living Room piano), 2001 Oct; 6_17; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Vienna Kreisel, 2006 Jan 05; 6_18; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Vienna Kreisel Outside Taxi Ride Cohendon Internet, 2006; 6_19; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Vienna Joan student, 2006; 6_20; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Dagfian, 6_21; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Godel vs Skolem Axium of Choice, 6_22; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Martin Davis, 2001 Oct 14; 6_23; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Martin Davis 2, 2001 Oct 14; 6_24; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - 4K Operation, 2004 Dec 12; 6_25; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen Short, 2006; 6_26; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen upstairs, 2001 Dec 10; 6_27; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen Rieman Hypo Living Room, 6_28; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen, 2001 Oct; 6_29; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Cohen Selberg, 2001 Oct 16; 6_30; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen piano, 2001 Oct; 6_31; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Godel Conference Panel Tape # 2 Kreisel McIntyre, 6_32; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Vienna Hilary Putnam Accordion Player, 2006; 6_33; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Vienna Swiss TV Gala Dinner, 2006; 6_34; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Godel Conference BRND Intro CAFE Tape # 1, 42852; 6_35; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Vienna hotel Room, Hotel Lobby Penrose Speech, 2006; 6_36; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Moschovakis Inside # 2, 2004 Sep 04; 6_37; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Choir at hospital Dag Finn Interview Part 2, 6_38; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Rudy Rucker, 2001 Nov; 6_39; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Richard Block, 6_40; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Cohen Speech Vienna Crowd Reaction, 2006; 6_41; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Vienna Café Top Press Conference hotel room, 2006; 6_42; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - PJ Cohen 1, 2001 Jul 01; 6_43; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Cohen, 2001 Oct 16; 6_44; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Moschovakis Inside # 1 Outside Randy, 2004 Sep 4; 6_45; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Dad 70 Restaurant; Party, 2004; 6_46; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Moschovakis Outside; Eric's Camera, 2004 Sep 4; 6_47; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen 31 oz Magic Moyel Childhood; Religion, 6_48; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Paul Cohen Home Choice Restaurant, 6_49; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Civil War, 6_50; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Larry Sanders - The Beginning of the End; As My Career Lay Dying; The Interview; Flip; The Final Episode, 6_60; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - VHS Yiddish Language - Motel The Operator, 6_61; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Item Burres Frank Llryz Wright, 6_62; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 6)
  - Various discs on spindle, optical disc(s) (Box 6)
- Computer files
  - New York Times Crossword Puzzles, 6_01; floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 6)
  - Paul J. Cohen Medical Images, 6_50; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - P Cohen Data Disk, 2007 Mar 27; 6_51; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - Cohan Photo's Complete, 2006 Sep 16; 6_52; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - Cohen 72 Photos Disk 1, 6_53; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - Cohen 72 All Photos, 6_54; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - Untitled, 6_55; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - Sweiz; Sweden, 6_56; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - Fields Medallists' Lectures, 6_57; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - Besuch Paul Christina, 2003 Aug; 6_58; optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 6)
  - Logic, Book, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Book, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Rosenberg Programs, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Language, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - QAPLUS, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Auto Biography Literary, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Documentary, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - ACE EXE from FOXPRO 2.5, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Photos, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - PROGL, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - ICU Utility Power Plus, 1995; 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - FoxPro Backup Disk, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Book, 2000 Sep 01; 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Foxpro Backup Disk 3, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Murphy Wed. Photos, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup FoxPro Disk 1, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - FoxPro Backup Disk 2, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Baclup 3 (System), 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - FoxPro Backup Disk 4, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - ICU Utility Power Plus (2 of 2), 1995; 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Book, 1998 Nov; 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Book, 1995; 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - MOUSE PROCOMM, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - pcohen.tex charles, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Disk 1, 2001 Aug 23; 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Windows Disk 4, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Math, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - DOS 3.20, 1991 Feb; 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup 8, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Paul 6, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Seer's Sojour, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup Vol. 9, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - JAC.Doc Interview w/ Tommy Jaquete, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Vol 6, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Organizer-3 PC-Outline, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup IV, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup V, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup 9, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - LIB Disk I QLIB.DOC QLIB.INI, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Willy the Worm, Willy Editor, Wizard, Qubert, Topgun Pinball, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup VIII, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup IX, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - PCTEX Disk #4, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup X, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup II, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup IV, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Backup VIII, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)
  - Untitled, 1 floppy disk(s) (3.5 inch) (Box 1)